Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good afternoon and a warm welcome on behalf of the Wisdom Seed, who are delighted to also welcome Sachin Radham Rinpoche this afternoon to teach us.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Alison Driscoll and it is my honor and delight to introduce Rinpoche to all of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's here for the first time in this region and we hope the first of many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: For those of you unfamiliar with the Wisdom Seat, we're a small group of eclectic Tibetan Buddhist practitioners in this area who realized a number of years ago a void that high lamas might go to New York, they might go to Boston, but they weren't coming to Philly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So our mission is to ensure to
[SPEAKER_00]: and to properly host high lamas in this area.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thank you for being here to show that that's appreciated.
[SPEAKER_00]:Shechen Rabjam is the grandson of Gyabje Dilgo Khyentse Rinpoche, as many of you know, one of the foremost Tibetan Buddhist masters of the 20th century.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rinpoche grew up with Dilgo Khyentse and from the age of three began receiving teachings and transmissions from him.
[SPEAKER_00]: With Dilgo Khyentse's passing in 1991 as the Dharma heir, Sachin Rabjam has assumed responsibility for transmitting Dilgo Khyentse's vast and profound teachings and bringing his vision for the preservation of Tibetan Buddhist teachings and culture to full fruition.
[SPEAKER_00]: As part of these responsibilities, Sachin Rabjam has been the abbot
[SPEAKER_00]: of all of theShechen monasteries and nunneries, I'm happy to say, the hub of which is in Nepal, and includes a shedra for academics, tanka painting, sacred dancing, rituals, and chants, and a medical clinic.
[SPEAKER_00]: To fulfill the vision of Dilgo Khyentse, he has also established the Dilgo Khyentse Fellowship to educate, inspire and preserve Tibetan Buddhist teachings and culture in all of its forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have brochures about the fellowship available on the registration table for those who are interested or would like to make a donation to support this mission.
[SPEAKER_00]: This afternoon Rinpoche will offer teachings on resting in the nature of mind, essential meditation instructions, his commentary on Dilgo Khyentse's teaching entitled Brilliant Moon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Copies of this have been made available to you, we hope you all have one, here today as a gift of the wisdom seat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you and now Rinpoche we request you to turn the wheel of the Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, let's relax a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I don't give much Dharma talks, especially in the West, so I don't have much to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is already like the fifth talk, so I think I finished everything I have to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, thank you, all of you, for coming here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And many of you came here because somehow many of you met Jyamshid Rinpoche, and many of you heard about him, and somehow many of you have some connection directly or indirectly to Khyentse Rinpoche, because Khyentse Rinpoche
[SPEAKER_01]: First of all, he is a non-sectarian master.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is a student from all the four schools, four major schools of Tibet Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_01]: And these days, most of the Dharambaches and lamas who travel around the West and give teachings, somehow, most of them have lineage directly from Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore,
[SPEAKER_01]: it sort of makes us somehow in the same lineage or same mandala.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here, yes, I spent many years with Khyentse Rinpoche since I was five till 25, till he passed away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I always say that I feel very, very lucky to be with him for so many years.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he is one of the best students, so therefore I am still not enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: But physically, I am sort of becoming like him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not inversely, not much development, but physically, yes, he was big and strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: His Holiness Dalai Lama said in his interview, he said, Oh, Khyentse Rinpoche, physically a very well-built body, always smiling, always smiling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I feel very fortunate and many of you, I think, from the different Sangha groups here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like I said, somehow, because of our teachers, we sort of bound spiritually.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I don't think you will need any more instruction on meditation because I think most of you have been studying with Tibetan masters for more than 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: So many of you have already heard so many teachings from the great masters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how did our great masters become what they are, who they are?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think it's anything to do with the Tibetan genes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think they became who they are and what they are because they practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: they studied their practice and I'm sure also Tibet environment also very peaceful very calm so maybe it helped enhance a lot to progress in their practice so likewise if we want to
[SPEAKER_01]: progress in our practice, progress in our kind of inner realization, then I think we have to follow in their footsteps and do practice more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I thought maybe I will just encourage you guys a little bit importance of, you know, practicing how important it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So just someone who can talk well, someone who can entertain, is not enough, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have lots of TV hosts who can entertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oprah Winfrey, even I get hooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's not about how much you can entertain, but how much you can actually give inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So just to remind you that of course all the Buddha's teaching, it is focused on training our mind, all the teachings of Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore, I think the
[SPEAKER_01]: All the Tibetan masters, so many, many years since Buddhadharma introduced into Tibet, they always try to practice, try to look inwards, and try to kind of not only practice, but then write instructions, texts, how to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So for many, many hundreds of years, the main thing was to develop inner realisation.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the same time, we had a nice tour the other day,
[SPEAKER_01]: Philadelphia, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you are signing the Constitution, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Declaration of Constitution.
[SPEAKER_01]: Declaration of Independence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Independence, which is wonderful, we all enjoy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same time maybe Jimmy Limbaugh was writing the launching thing in Tibet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you look at it from that perspective, we sort of went different directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: put our focus in different directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But of course, one had outer development result, another side had inner development result.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now it's sort of come together, thanks to many Masters who practice and flee Tibet and then come to West.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in a way, thanks to the Chinese problem in China, so that all the lamas came around the world and spread the Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in a way, if you look at it from the positive side, of course, a lot of monasteries destroyed and a lot of tragedy happened in Tibet, but the good side, the Dharma came to the West.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without that, maybe it might take longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So because they come to the West,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we are able to receive the teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think the most important thing is the teachings we have received
[SPEAKER_01]: So many teachings, so many instructions, so many books.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think the most important thing is how much we can really put into, absorb the teaching and help us, change us.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like I mentioned before, it is to train our mind to reduce our negative emotions,
[SPEAKER_01]: So after many years of practice, many years of meditation, if we become better human beings, if we have less attachment, less desire, less hatred, less anger, then I think we are going in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even though we spent 20 or 30 years with such an enlightened Master, if we still have those emotions very strong in us, then maybe our practice is not going very well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't think it doesn't really matter how high the title of the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mahamudra, Dzogbo Chembo, or it's just simple bodhicitta, mind training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it really helps us, or whatever can really change us, I think that practice is more relevant to us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course there is no kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: shortcut without progress slowly without taming our mind without reducing the negative emotions i don't think we will have a there's a kind of direct shortcut so some i being with cancer which i meet many practitioners many of his students each one is different
[SPEAKER_01]: Some, they're just simple practice, lojong, mind training practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a saying in Tibetan, when the circumstances arise, then you will see how good the practitioner is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when everything is going smooth, we don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01]: how well we are doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When some circumstances arise, then we can handle it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that means we have some kind of achievement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a good horseman, if you're very good at riding a horse.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Tibet, they can ride a horse even without the saddle.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much horse jump, the people can always handle it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, when some circumstances arise, when some difficulty we face in our life, then that time I think we have to utilize what we have learned, what we have heard, what we have practiced.
[SPEAKER_01]: Khyentse Rinpoche always advised on mingle your mind with Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mingle your mind with Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that means whatever circumstances arise, somehow it should remind us of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then if our practice stays in altar when you are sitting, when you are in reality world life, then if we cannot control the emotions, lose control of anger,
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I think it's not really helping.
[SPEAKER_01]: So mingle your mind with dharma is whenever some kind of circumstances arise, then we always try to bring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So circumstances doesn't always mean bad circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good circumstances, bad circumstances, whatever, even good circumstances,
[SPEAKER_01]: something good happened to you, you should always try to think, oh, thanks to the Buddha Dharma, thanks to three jewels, and if bad circumstances arise, oh, due to my karma, purify my karma, like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Tibetan it says, , means happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also bring that into a path without feeling guilt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then if some difficulty comes in life, also if you can bring that into a path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then how to bring that into a path?
[SPEAKER_01]: All the teachings talk about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: and one very useful, I think, in the mind-training practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always says how to handle when some difficult thing arises in our life.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are three main kinds of methods using the antidote of negative emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: by which we sort of fight against the negative emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then another one, by recognizing the negative emotions and thoughts, then using that into your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: then in maybe kind of higher Vajrayana view, using the negative emotions or negative things, transforming them into wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So all these methods are taught.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure most of you heard many, many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now I think that we can immediately put into practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that way, I think we will see how we progress
[SPEAKER_01]: And we will be the best judge ourselves, because nobody can see our mind, how it goes inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can look like a good practitioner from outwardly, then inwardly full of negative things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes we see the people doing circumambulation around the stupa,
[SPEAKER_01]: with mala.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is Asian people I'm talking about, in Nepal or Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the mala is in one hand, and then the whole time they are gossiping.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone is good, someone is not good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you hear that?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then your rosary became very smooth, but our mind is not smooth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this can happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Outwardly, you never know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Outwardly, you look, oh, very diligent, very kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes we can sort of, with our kind of pride and negative emotions, can make us do practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I don't practice, people will criticize.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then all our intentions are wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that, I think...
[SPEAKER_01]: Again and again we have to analyze our mind, how it's going.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we'll be the best judge of our own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then again also our Dhamma brothers and sisters can also kind of, if your good spiritual brothers and sisters genuinely kind of carry each other, then you can point out a little bit, but be careful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some common problem we all face, now we know how precious dharma is, we know how important it is to practice, but somehow we don't feel like practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this question was put up once to Chabji Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember in Nepal, how can I really engage myself into practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know how to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I received all the instructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have bell and dorje, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how can I really engage myself into practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: So I remember Rinpoche saying, bringing our mind into practice, it is the thinking of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: always try to remember impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even in Sutra, Buddha said the monk's attitude should always be towards impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, I think impermanence is really kind of key or the main kind of mentor, I don't know if that's the English word, right, to put our mind into practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now we have seen many of our friends who are no longer with us.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were there last year, they are not here this year.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we never know when we are going to leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once somebody else, went to see Chabje Dudjom Rinpoche, and this guy was crying.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Rinpoche said, What happened?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, Oh, doctor told me I will only live three years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he was crying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, Dudjom Rinpoche says, Oh, good for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know you're going to live three years.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know whether I'll live till tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that, I think as a practitioner, every day I think we have to sort of remind us impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then that sort of, are we ready when the time comes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sooner or later we have to go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think this kind of attitude, this kind of thinking would really bring our mind into Dharma and how important it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I read somewhere, it's not a Buddhist magazine or Dharma magazine, I read somewhere, they said that people make preparations way ahead of time, especially if you are going on holiday to Hawaii or somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already start making reservations, the hotel, booking of the aeroplane.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a short holiday, it's like one month or maximum, or one week, and you come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's a holiday which you are never going to come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't really prepare.
[SPEAKER_01]: Preparation, no preparation for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I thought it's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-Buddhist magazine, even they say like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think thinking of impermanence will turn our mind into dharma, turn our mind into engaging into practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So of course all the four thoughts in the ngondro practice are very important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, many of you are already in the path, practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think, as you might already know, the path is very clearly laid out, step by step.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that layout is done by, like I mentioned before,
[SPEAKER_01]: the best mind engineers designed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just somebody randomly decided, saying, oh, that sounds better, or that sounds easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: Starting with shamatha practice, which is, the other day I mentioned, I think very much relevant in our kind of modern society.
[SPEAKER_01]: where we have so many things going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think the calmness of our mind is the first step, the basis for all the practice, the place to grow the light seed, the base of shamatha practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And many Rinpoches who lived in the West, who know the Western people,
[SPEAKER_01]: who know the Western culture, emphasize in shamatha, which is not so much in Tibet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I understand when I go to Tibet, the area is naturally shamatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is not much distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, if you are in Tibet, if you don't practice, there is nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here we have TV or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise boring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the environment in Tibet is a little bit different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I think the West, many lamas introducing shamatha practice as a start, preliminary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course, most of the structure then comes moindra practice, preliminary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's accumulation, there's a number, there's a postation, mandala, of course, all those things
[SPEAKER_01]: are important, but I think ngondro, the real ngondro is the four thoughts or four changes of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: What should turn our mind into dharma?
[SPEAKER_01]: To become a really good practitioner, proper practitioner, the four thoughts should be the main reason why you turn our mind into dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how we will have a sense of renunciation of this samsara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise it's not really becoming a real serious practitioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So precious human life, which you heard so many times, precious human life, impermanence, law of cause and effect, and then the suffering of the samsara.
[SPEAKER_01]: So these four thoughts, I think we should really put importance in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not only the numbers become the most important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think the most important is the four changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And these four thoughts...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry, maybe I'm not...
[SPEAKER_01]: saying the name properly, because my translation went to Croatia.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only this body and mind, speech is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think it's four thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think the four thoughts should really, by thinking on the four thoughts, that sort of turns our mind into Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, all of us, I think we can say, who are not raised as a Buddhist, who come to a Buddhist, come because they have some kind of understanding of samsara, and then they want some kind of realization.
[SPEAKER_01]: some notion of what we call the renunciation that's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: A little bit different from the monastic, where we put the young monks in the monastery, they have no idea what the samsara is, they have no idea of renunciation, so we teach them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then some of them get into dharma, and some of them are more interested in the relative world, so they leave the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you guys already have that kind of thing when you join them, when you come to the study of the Buddha Dharma, because there is some sense of something which is not right in the samsaric world.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that thought I think we should not forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: what brings us into dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of some kind of dissatisfaction, feeling of samsara, that's what turns into...
[SPEAKER_01]: So in order to have more engagement to dharma, I think we have to remind that of oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The best way is to focus on the four thoughts of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I also, sometimes I joke with the friends, because the classic way of
[SPEAKER_01]: There are four thoughts, precious human life.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are five favorable and five unfavorable, eight in this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think from a modern science point of view, that how the evolution slowly starts from... Matthew is my good friend, so I always ask the modern science point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm very interested.
[SPEAKER_01]: how the small cell slowly, slowly turned into fish and how fish slowly turned into kind of something moving, slowly became, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said there are millions of chance of that cell not becoming human.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are millions of chances that we become a mushroom, or we become a tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So from that perspective, if you look at what we are, so much human intelligence, so much potential in our brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think it's not just born, live, die.
[SPEAKER_01]: So not much meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then again, we are a little bit better kind of a tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: A tree at least brings oxygen.
[SPEAKER_01]: We consume oxygen and pollute the world and live.
[SPEAKER_01]: So not so much used to be born in human.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that, from a modern point of view, I think whatever makes us turn into dharma, we should look from different angles.
[SPEAKER_01]: and think from different angles.
[SPEAKER_01]: From a science point of view, it makes sense that how important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then impermanence, everything changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impermanence is not always bad news.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of impermanence, poor becomes rich.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of impermanence, rich becomes poor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of impermanence, everything can function like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the impermanence, I think, is something that is always changing, constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We talk about, oh, last year during this time we did that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Last year during this time doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Last year is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: This year is new.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tomorrow is something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that, I think, contemplating on impermanence, the changes, everything changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding of everything impermanent changing, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this kind of attitude or this kind of thinking in the mind, we start looking at everything a little bit differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: We start looking at the world differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like going into a food supermarket after lunch and before lunch.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go before lunch, you buy all the foodstuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go after lunch, you don't want to look at the foodstuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you look at the world with the impermanent in mind, you will start looking at the world a little bit differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: And without this impermanent understanding, you will start looking differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, law of the cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing becomes something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything has cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even a small thing, I think we said that even a small spark of fire can burn a mountain of grass.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, I think the law of cause and effect is very important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we have to be very careful.
[SPEAKER_01]: really makes sense because law and cause and effect very much depends on our intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, I think again, checking our intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever we do, I think with a positive intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And our mind can be very, very tricky, so that very careful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes we do some kind of big generosity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then if our intention is purely generosity, want to help, or you want to be in the Facebook.
[SPEAKER_01]: So these things can be very, very tricky.
[SPEAKER_01]: So karma always works in a mysterious way.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was this one man who was interviewed in France on the radio.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that person was interviewed just before my friend, Dharma brother Matthew.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matthew was waiting outside and this person was interviewed on the radio.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why he was interviewed is that in his life,
[SPEAKER_01]: he's been through 40 different tragedies, but he still survived.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever there's a big fire, he happened to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever there's a big earthquake, he happened to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where there's a big accident, he happened to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he was admitted to hospital, the nurse gave him the wrong diagnosis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then something, something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: One after another, 40 different tragedies.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is the kind of people we should now go with together.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I mean is the many kinds of karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's quite interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes karma is like we can't really see something happening in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you hear this kind of story, it's really like karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand more of karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then when you hear the different people who went through when there was a tragedy or something, each and every one has a different story.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people just left two seconds before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people just arrived one minute before and died.
[SPEAKER_01]: So karma, I think, is very much, even we cannot really see it right now, but if you really think about it, it's very much, and also very logical.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the suffering of samsara, as long as we have attachments, greed and all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is the richest man in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: We think the more wealth we have, we will be happier.
[SPEAKER_01]: The richest man in the world is not necessarily the happiest person.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most powerful man in the world is not necessarily the happiest person.
[SPEAKER_01]: So these things are just in front of our eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we don't need a big philosophical idea behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we can just look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So these things are very much, I think, relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you think about all these things, then naturally you feel what we call the sense of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Should I tell the Indian restaurant story, Vivian?
[SPEAKER_01]: Indian restaurant, my favorite subject.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told before, so maybe I can repeat again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many of you didn't hear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'd like to compare the renunciation feeling to some kind of Indian restaurant.
[SPEAKER_01]: In India, when you travel far in an Indian bus, on an Indian road, shaking every day, all the time, with the dust and all that, then you feel very tired, very hungry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then there are restaurants on the roadside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Daba, they call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more pot they have, the more dishes they have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you count the pot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's seven pots, so they have seven dishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you stop the bus and you come to the restaurant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the curry smells so good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you been to Indian restaurants?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then irresistible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say mouth-watering?
[SPEAKER_01]: and you're so hungry, irresistible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So sometimes when you look at the samsara, it's irresistible, very flashy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you go behind the Indian restaurant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a big guy sweating on the way, they're making the chapati with their feet.
[SPEAKER_01]: and then the water is not clean, the fly is just flying from the toilet to the kitchen, going back and forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then after you see the background, you come back and then you lose your appetite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't need to force yourself feeling, ah, I shouldn't eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you see the defaults or the dirty, then naturally you feel kind of disgust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So similarly, the samsaric, what we think brings happiness, more wealth, more fame, more this, more that, then if you really see the behind, what's going on in the kitchen, then sort of naturally you feel like,
[SPEAKER_01]: sort of, this is not really what we want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think what we call the sense of renunciation becomes easier, detached feeling from the samsaric world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think these are very skillful means of helping our mind, how to turn our mind into dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is the real ngondro, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, of course, we do the accumulation, Vajrasattva, all those things are like a method.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the real mantra, I think, is to make you turn your mind to dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the essence of the ...
[SPEAKER_01]: Essence, the most important thing of the lower three yanas, if you think of the first yana, the most important thing is having a sense of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, how to be free from the suffering of samsara, oneself and the other sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not only oneself, but other sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then that's where the bodhicitta comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think the more kind of stronger bodhicitta you will feel when you see there is a possibility of coming out of the samsara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes we talk about emptiness, chunyata, then people say, oh, everything is empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why we should practice compassion?
[SPEAKER_01]: So the more you understand emptiness intellectually, experience, of course, intellectually, the more you understand emptiness, then you see the more possibility that people can reach liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore, the more you understand emptiness, the more you feel compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: One example that His Holiness the Dalai Lama in the teaching, very helpful, was an example of one guy falling in the ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this person is going to drown.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you are watching from here.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you feel sorry, you feel pity, so sad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now he is drowning, he is dying, so sad.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing much we can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then there is an island next to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If this guy turns that way, there is a possibility that he will survive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you feel more strong kind of feeling, oh, I wish he would just turn that way so he can get out of this drowning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, when we see the possibility of liberation, the more we see the possibility of liberation, the more stronger compassion we will feel because we see there is a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I think that's possibility, not only oneself, but sharing with all sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is, I think it's called bodhicitta, it's wants to bring all sentient beings into liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to really have a bodhicitta mind, I think you really have to accept or sort of understand this possibility, and that becomes bodhicitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, just compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is, I think, whatever practice we do, we have to set our goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: We practice for the sake of all mother sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: which I think last time I mentioned, like Khyentse Rinpoche, when he started teaching, he always again and again went on about setting our goal right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever we do is not for oneself, it's for the sake of all mother sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: His voice is very deep.
[SPEAKER_01]: We heard this so many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when we were young, we said, why should we go on and on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't we go to the main point?
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think it is every time we practice, we have to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how we set our practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without this kind of bodhicitta mind, then I don't know, our purpose of practice may be a little bit off the track.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in order to set on the track, I think we have to set our bodhicitta mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then we are on the right track, or the Buddhist path.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we heard so many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, the little I understand Dharma, I understand how important it is, setting our goal in precious bodhicitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what we call the generating compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why all sentient beings?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why not only me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why sentient beings?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's some logical reason, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because every kind of happiness that we enjoy, even relative happiness, depends on others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without others, we will not have happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we were born alone in the mountain with nobody else, we might go crazy, unless you are a practitioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So everything, I think, people who build the house, we enjoy here.
[SPEAKER_01]: under this shade.
[SPEAKER_01]: People who build cars, we enjoy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So everything depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is due to others that we feel happy and comfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then when you think from Dharma point of view, or Buddhist point of view,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without bodhicitta, there's no way to get enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in order to practice bodhicitta without sentient beings, there's no way you can have this kind of broad mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just feel pity to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to bring you anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the broader our mind is, that somehow sort of, you feel our own suffering, our own pain less, because your mind is opened up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the glass of water, you put one handful of salt in it, it's undrinkable, because it becomes salty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, our mind, when you focus just to oneself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I was little suffering, little pain, it was unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even someone says some few words, you get angry because you're so kind of self-centered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even a bonk from the car can make you go crazy.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you put the salt, the same amount of salt, in a big bucket of water, you cannot taste the salt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you think of all sentient beings, your personal suffering becomes much less, much smaller.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the scientific research also says, people who always, you know, normal friends, normal conversations, some people always say, oh, I did this, I did that, I, always bring I.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some people have a little bit less I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Talk about less me, me, I, I.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have less chance of getting heart attacks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think too much self-centre is not good for health also.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think that's why the bodhicitta mind is very important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So essence of bodhicitta is what we call caring for others.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's the right translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So first essence of the first jnana is to have renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Essence of the bodhicitta is for caring others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then those who sort of engage into more vajrayana practice,
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are different methods in Vajrayana practice, going into, how do you say, receiving empowerment from authentic Master, authentic lineage, someone who has achieved enlightened mind, through which we receive the Vajrayana empowerment, introduction to Vajrayana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in Vajrayana practices, also more kind of complex meditation with the different deities and mandalas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mainly, I think the most important thing in the Vajrayana practice is to develop the pure vision or pure perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it pure perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: So seeing everything as a learning Buddhafield,
[SPEAKER_01]: So this method, once we were in another Dhamma talk in another place, not this time, but a long time ago, and there was this gentleman from African-American, with a kind of Jamaican hat, sitting in front of me, and very seriously taking note,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he asked a question, he said, Hi Lama, what you are talking about is high-tech compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Vajrayana is a little bit like high-tech practice, very complex, but very schoolful means.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is in order to transform one's all kind of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think what we see phenomena, everything is due to our ignorant mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't really can relate to the pure perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the essence of Vajrayana practice is what we call development stage, which is to transform everything into the two things, which is the pure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So instead of we are sort of whitewashing all the phenomena, I think what we are trying to do in developing Vajrayana practice is to see the reality of the phenomena, which is the pure perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So due to our kind of negative emotions and negative thoughts that we are seeing everything negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here we are not trying to achieve
[SPEAKER_01]: or gain something here, when you practice, you are trying to remove something, which is the negative emotions, or negative ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you remove the negative ignorance, then you start seeing the reality, which is the pure perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that is the Vajrayana method.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, within the Vajrayana practice, there is a development stage and a completion stage, which comes very much with
[SPEAKER_01]: meditating in the true nature state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think this teaching here, short teaching, is very much related with the Vajrayana accomplishment stage practice according to our Khyentse Rinpoche's lineage or tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I will sort of go through the text
[SPEAKER_01]: a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't think, I don't want to add, I don't know, and also I don't want to add too much to the profound words of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, in Tibetan, the meaning of the content is much shorter, and English is already explained.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if I'm speaking Tibetan, I can speak more, but when I speak in English, the translation is already translated.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the commentary is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here it says that So I think usually this kind of teaching is given
[SPEAKER_01]: to the people who really want to know a little bit more about the nature of mind, or we can say about the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Guru will instruct to see the body, and speech, and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Physical body, the speech that we talk, and then the things we think, that is our mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, body and speech is like a servant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here when we do this kind of introduction teaching, this particular kind of teaching, there's not so much explanation about the philosophical background.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sort of direct kind of teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore, it is simply said, body, speech, mind, which is more important.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course, most people come up with the mind is more important, and the body and the speech is like a servant, so mind controls everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when you look back into your mind, who is looking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of looking outwardly, you turn your mind inwardly, and then watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing to see, but it is clear light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it like that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Thought there is nothing to see, it is vividly clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I will not read the English one, because then these words
[SPEAKER_01]: beyond my knowledge of English.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I will use the simple English that what I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how to look into one's own mind is without sort of fabricating or without kind of just relax and look into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you sit like that, looking back into one's mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: Something can trigger, like sound or something could trigger our mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our mind goes there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even nothing triggers our mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some thoughts arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look at the nature of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look back at the nature of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: When even the thought arises, it does not obscure the nature to nature or inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let it arise and let it go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite often, Khyentse Rinpoche would compare throwing a stone at the dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you throw a stone at the dog, the dog will chase the stone.
[SPEAKER_01]: When thoughts arise, if you continue with thoughts, the thought will bring another thought, another thought, there will be chain reaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you throw a stone at a lion, the lion look at you, doesn't chase the stone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you don't want to throw the second stone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when thought arise, you look back, and then the second thought will not arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So without dwelling into past thoughts, without bringing future thoughts, past thought means like, oh, I've done this, I've made this, yesterday I did this, and thinking like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Future thought, oh, I want to do this in the future things.
[SPEAKER_01]: just without dwelling into past, without thinking the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking at just present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is called the fourth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is called the
[SPEAKER_01]: four paths without three.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you have four paths without three, three is the past, present, future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you're not dwelling in the past, not going in the future, and being in the present itself, also, that is called the fourth path without three.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then look at the nature of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So one way of dealing with the thoughts is first recognize the thoughts, thought arise, and then where does it come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does it drill?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does it go?
[SPEAKER_01]: It sort of appears, but you will never find where it's born, you will never find where it's gone, and you will never find where it's due, because if it's never born, then it's never gone, and it's never due.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yet you somehow feel there is something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But these kinds of thoughts will never affect the true nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking at the
[SPEAKER_01]: naked Jamba.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this experience, the naked, I think, naked Rambab Jambandi, how to carry on in this practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you sit and practice, we do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then when we are into our daily life, time to time kind of remind us
[SPEAKER_01]: Again and again, when we were waiting for a bus, waiting for an airplane, or I don't know, always there's a moment where you're really not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't have to bring the cushion and altar and put it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just sit wherever you are and look back.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how I think bringing the experience into daily life, time to time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can set your watch every hour.
[SPEAKER_01]: So by doing it, by doing like that, by training again and again, then your thought will naturally be liberated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes we give the example of putting a knot on a snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you make a knot on a snake, the snake can undo by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will get used to that and then you will get confident that when thought arises, when you look at it, it naturally disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then to enhance that kind of experience, mingle your one's mind with Guru's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mingle one's mind with Guru's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Tibetan we say, there's a hundred teacher on the ground and one teacher in my heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we can receive teaching from different teachers, different masters, but there should always be one in our heart, which we call the root guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I always tell people, it not necessarily has to be physically there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like Chabje Khyentse Rinpoche, I usually, to people who want to learn something from me, I usually recommend Chabje Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: And likewise, many other teachers, really great masters, are very hard to find these days.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we can be, whoever guru that really inspire you, that guru can be your kind of object.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know whether we can say object or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That guru can be your source of inspiration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because guru is who really will guide you into enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's someone who is one with the dharma,
[SPEAKER_01]: One, his life with the Dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, there are many gurus like that during Khyentse Rinpoche's time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm talking about Khyentse Rinpoche because that's who I felt this connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will really trust 100% that he will not misguide you towards your path.
[SPEAKER_01]: 100% confident.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you naturally feel very drawn into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we are this kind of confident, even in our life, the smaller confidence we have, we trust the New York cab drivers will take you from destination A to B.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might be a little bit rough driver, but that's why we get into the cab.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we think the driver is a little bit drunk or something, we're not going to get in the truck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an aeroplane, we trust the pilot.
[SPEAKER_01]: with our life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to take from A to B.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here Guru is like a pilot who will take from samsara to nirvana.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of trust.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that trust I think we find in some really enlightened masters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And which many of us were lucky to meet many of these energy masters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I always say, even physically, they are not in life or with us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their teachings, their methods, their path which lay for us are very much there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then thanks to modern technology, we have the videos, we have the photos, we can at least know how they look like.
[SPEAKER_01]: We used to get very annoyed with Matthew running around with a camera.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is this monk doing always with a camera?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why not paying attention to teaching?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is he always bringing this tape recorder and always recording?
[SPEAKER_01]: We didn't have good gadgets.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pity, no?
[SPEAKER_01]: When we have these gadgets, now there's nothing to record.
[SPEAKER_01]: When we had some great masters, we didn't have these gadgets.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at least we have some.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I use my music tape to over-record Khyentse Rinpoche's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nowadays when we listen to Rinpoche teaching, suddenly Madonna comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I was young, we used to listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So those things now become very precious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Buddha, he said, you know, if I die,
[SPEAKER_01]: When I leave, I leave you the Vinaya, as you are, as my regent.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have materials now, not only text, videos, footages.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this will sort of inspire us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we feel very close, inspired.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to come naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just Google them, or not just flyer that you believe in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you feel that, then that's where you mingle your mind with the Guru's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And ultimately, all the Guru says, you get your inner Guru, then you don't need outer Guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in order to get close to inner Guru, we need the support of outer Guru, someone who can speak, someone who looks like a human, someone who we can relate to, someone who feels called, someone who acts like us.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Vajrayana practice we say that you see the guru like a Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guru like a Guru Rinpoche or Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have that kind of feeling towards a really enlightened guru, then all the practice becomes very easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even the deity is a manifestation of guru.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can relate with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So hard to find, but still possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mingle one's mind with Guru's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then through that you feel strong devotion, ultimate devotion, ultimate faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will really guide us into the enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then ultimately,
[SPEAKER_01]: through this kind of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then here again, Khyentse Rinpoche reminds us, again and again, we should think of impermanence, renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then if you have the vows, the law of the conduct, follow them, digitally, not jumping into the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always follow the conduct.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it called?
[SPEAKER_01]: Law and conduct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Conduct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Follow them carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: The essence practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put practice intelligently.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Khyentse Rinpoche always recommend, and many masters recommend, listen to teaching, contemplate, practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in the retreat, Khyentse Rinpoche always recommend us to read the texts, understand, contemplate meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then somehow enhance our practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will enhance one another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here we are not trying to get intellectual understanding of different views of different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, when you read a book, you read about the mind, about the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore it will enhance one another.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also says that
[SPEAKER_01]: So it looks like this letter was written to some kind of Rinpoche or some master who has been practicing the way Rinpoche addressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most of the Khyentse Rinpoche's letters are like that, always advice and teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we benefit from these teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ultimately we say that don't expect the result first, meditate till you die.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then dharma becomes part of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think that's it with a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry for my Pakistani English.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody in Napa Valley, one time I met a Christian priest and we were talking to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And suddenly he stopped and said, why are you speaking Pakistani English?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I have an Indian accent, so maybe the priest has been to Pakistan.
[SPEAKER_01]: So anyway, we'll keep some question and answer if you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's something I can answer, I will try my best.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_03]: I wonder if you would be kind enough to say a little bit about the Khyentse Yangtze, and the responsibility you had of raising him, and how he is now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like Chabji Khyentse Rinpoche always makes everything easy for me, it wasn't difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding him was no problem at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: This story I like to tell.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I don't tell, I forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: When Khyentse Rinpoche was recognized by Jyotish Rinpoche, Khyentse Rinpoche told me,
[SPEAKER_01]: to inform first Queen Mother and King of Bhutan, because they are the disciples of Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then after that, inform His Holiness Dalai Lama.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then after, I have to inform the other heads of the different schools, because since Khyentse Rinpoche is very much related with all the four different schools, major schools.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I went to fly to Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_01]: I met the King of Bhutan, the Royal Grandmother.
[SPEAKER_01]: I explained to them, this is my journey, one week.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I was returning from Bhutan in the airplane.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was sitting next to the home minister of Bhutan.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, why are you here?
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, I came to inform Queen Mother about Khyentse Rinpoche's reincarnation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I arrived in Delhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: I flew, I dropped to Dharamsala where His Holiness Dalai Lama was staying.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the way, His Holiness Penor Rinpoche happened to be in Bir.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just happened to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lives in South India.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is like, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: San Francisco and New York.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he happened to be in Bir.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I went to see Penor Rinpoche and I told him Khyentse Rinpoche was found.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I was going into his own Dalai Lama's chamber.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was waiting in the waiting room.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole Tibetan cabinet came to the meeting room.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will have an appointment after me with His Holiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why are you here?
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, I came here to inform Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I came to inform His Holiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, of course, His Holiness Dalai Lama knew, but I had to officially inform him that it's Portugal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I informed His Holiness Dalai Lama and I was coming out.
[SPEAKER_01]: His Holiness was coming in.
[SPEAKER_01]: head of the Trikunkaji tradition, who is also the disciple of Khyentse Rinpoche, very close.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, why are you doing here?
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, oh, I came to inform Khyentse Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reincarnation was born, so I came to inform him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I went down to Delhi, and that day, Bhutan's National Day, so the Bhutanese embassy invited me to the dinner party, which happened to be, and Bhutan foreign minister and vice president of India was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't ask me anything, but I thought this...
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought it was a good, tempted, you know, meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, who's left?
[SPEAKER_01]: Kamapa.
[SPEAKER_01]: That time Kamapa wasn't there, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the airport, going to Nepal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delhi airport.
[SPEAKER_01]: I checked in, suddenly I saw him, he was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, what are you doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, oh, I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: So he makes everything easy for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was born just next door neighbor.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was sort of expecting I would have to ride yaks and go into, you know, nomad.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is name of your father?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is name of your mother?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just next door neighbor.
[SPEAKER_01]: So previous Khyentse Rinpoche makes everything very easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So not much difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I spent 20 years with previous Khyentse Rinpoche and then 20 years with Yangtze Rinpoche.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now I'm semi-retired and Kempo is in charge of the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I try to focus a little bit more on practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the teachings that I receive, so many teachings I receive, I cannot count.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I want to put a little bit into practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I try to do a little bit of retreat, and then at the same time, I'm trying to transmit.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is not a very intellectual unit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to read the taxes, you know, the loong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm trying to give loongs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that also I learn a lot, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: would start his day early in the morning, and the whole day he would give teaching and all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And during the loong, he would give, I don't know, last time we had a meeting discussing about his life with Dzongse Khyentse Rinpoche and a few other lamas.
[SPEAKER_01]: We sort of counted how many teachings he gave in one day, and he gave 13 different teachings to different groups in one day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we thought it was normal until I started giving teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is not like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, hello.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been practicing a very, very long time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I find it very challenging.
[SPEAKER_03]: My mother recently passed away.
[SPEAKER_03]: Tremendous attachment, obviously, that I have to her.
[SPEAKER_03]: And she was a person that was extremely virtuous her entire life.
[SPEAKER_03]: I always have to work on myself dealing with patience and anger and jealousy.
[SPEAKER_03]: She never had those energies.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there some way, even though she didn't practice dharma, fortunately, because of my dear friendship with the Dalai Lama and bringing him to Israel and everything, she got to meet him a few times.
[SPEAKER_03]: But she never practiced dharma.
[SPEAKER_03]: So is there anything different that I can do or a certain practice I can do to sort of assist her in her, wherever she is or going or whatever?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because about 40 years ago, my father died and I had all these lamas helped him and
[SPEAKER_03]: I was very more spiritually materialist.
[SPEAKER_03]: I wanted to know where he was.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to know any of this now.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just want to know, how can I help her, really?
[SPEAKER_03]: Her name was Jean Pagan.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's very challenging for me, probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sometimes there's some people who don't call themselves Buddhists, but they are more Buddhists than some of us.
[SPEAKER_01]: So she's naturally a good kind person.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure she'll have a good rebirth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can do dedicated prayers to her and do practice dedicated to her.
[SPEAKER_03]: I also just want to mention I don't have everything right now that I'm inheriting yet that we're both working on this, but we certainly intend in the future to have a place between Europe and India where people can stop in Israel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Israel?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, we want to go there.
[SPEAKER_03]: We want to go there, and we have homes, and we have other obstacles to getting money from these homes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Both of us own homes, so we want to...
[SPEAKER_03]: maybe have a place for them to come.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we just hope when this happens, we can write to you and let you know if you could change planes there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because we've just saw thousands.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because after I brought the Dalai Lama to Israel 20 years ago, thousands of them come to Dharamsala now.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they have centers there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they stay there after the army to try to get rid of the mentality of the army.
[SPEAKER_03]: And thousands of these young people come there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're Israeli?
[SPEAKER_03]: He is, and my ancestors were.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I've been there 10 times already.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK. Make an escalation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And fortunately, I'm lucky enough to help bring the Dalai Lama there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I just hope I can bring you there too.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm very happy to meet you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to let you know, I've been there once already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you so much for your teachings.
[SPEAKER_03]: I had two questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: I work as a therapist, and I have meditated since I was a little kid.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I wanted to know two things.
[SPEAKER_03]: One, how to help people when they are sort of using meditation to suppress their feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's the first question.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're bypassing their negative emotions through meditation.
[SPEAKER_03]: or through other means, like pushing them down, oh, I'm peaceful, I'm peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: But actually they have a lot of stuff that they're not working with.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's my first question.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how to help myself when that's what's happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: And two, in terms of attachments,
[SPEAKER_03]: connected to what you said, but also I had been thinking the same thing when you were talking about renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing I find, and also everybody who comes into my office, whether they're coming from a war zone or they had some trauma or whatever it is, what they really want is they want their relationship, their marriage or their partnership to go well.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm trying to differentiate that good bodhicitta and caring about good relationships and being attached in a way that's not helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: So how to work with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that a renunciation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bodhicitta, when we include more people sometimes in your kind of loving kindness, sometimes people feel that you are neglecting your loved ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think bodhicitta means like
[SPEAKER_01]: the more you have kind of openness and loving kindness, the someone who is near to you will benefit more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean that taking part of your love from your loved one and giving it to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think when you increase this kind of loving kindness, meditation or thought, then someone who is close to you will affect more, like the sunrise.
[SPEAKER_01]: without bias, can we say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It shines everywhere, but someone who is closer to the sun gets better sun tan.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think the bodhicitta can work always, and it brings more love and more benefit to someone who is close to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Khenpo's Remindment, you also like that kind of disagreement or family problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not really like renunciation, it's kind of temperamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So impermanence, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: But of course, Buddhist practice can work in many levels, many layers.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here I'm talking to become the ultimate practitioner, then renounce the world and go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are practices where you can still practice being in the worldly life.
[SPEAKER_01]: because we are not ready to become Milarepa yet, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are a lot of skillful ways and many of, I think, the past Masters teach how to practice and also live in the worldly life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are teachings by some of the Masters how to do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the first question I had about numbing, I know people who have, whether it's with their child or their partner or whoever, they are doing their practice over here, maybe even completion stage practice, but over here in their relationships, they're numbed and cold and not really connecting.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm
[SPEAKER_03]: It seems like a spiritual materialism bypassing, so how to...
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think this is very much what I sort of described.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think if we have genuinely put our practice in right tech, it should naturally give us less negative emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if our negative emotions are still very much alive, then maybe you need to focus more on mind training, lojong practice, which can be more practical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practical in worldly life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Day to day problem you face?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think step by step, very detailed, clearly mentioned in the Lojong practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So sometimes our views go a bit too high up.
[SPEAKER_01]: In reality we can't handle the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that the teachings are high teachings given to a certain kind of person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Khyentse Rinpoche always says, you don't feed a steak to a baby.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feed the milk and you slowly, slowly, I don't know, then you slowly, slowly, eventually when you grow up, you give him a steak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So likewise, I think, according to our capacity, that's why the Buddha has taught in many different layers or levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So according to the needs of the beings, it's not something is better and something is worse, but it is whatever you can relate with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some of the shunyatas not even mention to the Shavas Kharo because they cannot accept.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too big.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all like that, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's from Israel?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but he's here now because of...
[SPEAKER_01]: He was born in Budapest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Todar.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you in Israeli.
[SPEAKER_03]: We wanted to know if you wanted to play some music at the end, the way Krishna does it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to go back to the big apple.
[SPEAKER_01]: So anyway, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think finished now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Program finished.
[SPEAKER_03]: If we have a teacher who's quite elderly and we still feel like when they pass we're going to need hands-on instruction, a root guru, and we don't know when they're going to
[SPEAKER_03]: reincarnate, what would be the best way of handling further practice during that period?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, when your guru suddenly, the spiritual master suddenly disappears, of course, because we still have the relative world, so we feel sad and all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in another way, like when Khyentse Rinpoche was alive,
[SPEAKER_01]: He was always somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: We think, oh, today he's in Bhutan, or I'm in India.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when he passes, he's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he becomes portable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever you go, he's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you so much for your teachings.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just have a quick request.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your teaching in New York and here and the Wongs have been so wonderful.
[SPEAKER_03]: I hope you've had a fantastic and wonderful welcoming stay and that you come back again soon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Philadelphia cheesesteak, I have to come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be a witness.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that very note, having taken the words right out of my mouth, Rinpoche, thank you so very much for your wisdom, humor, and compassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's been really wonderful to be with you this afternoon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on behalf of the Wisdom Seed and everyone here who has been so generous and appreciative in having you here this afternoon, please accept this humble offering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on behalf of the Wisdom Seat, if you are interested in any...
[SPEAKER_00]: Happy birthday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you for the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every day is a birthday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, for all of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, on behalf of the Wisdom Seed, if you're interested in our ongoing events, thewisdomseed.org is the website.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one coming up is a retreat to Rinpoche's point of practice is the essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at the end of the year, we have an opportunity for a week-long retreat and details and registration on the website.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything else?
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you again Rinpoche so much and please come again and again and again.